Guide to the Larry Spruch Papers MC.209
New York University Archives
Larry Spruch Papers
1943-2006
1950-2002
New York University Archives
Spruch, Larry
MC.209
54.5 Linear Feet
18.8. Gigabytes
The Larry Spruch Papers document the teaching and research activities of theoretical physicist and New York University professor Larry Spruch (1923-2006). Spruch taught physics at NYU from 1950 until his retirement in 1994. He is best known for his developments in scattering theory, investigations of Casimir forces, and contributions to the problem of determining necessary conditions for the existence of bound states.
Scope and Content
The Larry Spruch Papers contain diverse materials generated throughout Spruch's career. The materials date from between 1943, when Spruch enrolled in the University of Pennsylvania as a Ph.D. candidate in physics, and 2004, two years before Spruch's death. They document Spruch's activities as a Professor of Physics at New York University; as a prominent researcher into aspects of theoretical nuclear and particle physics and astrophysics; as a frequent presenter and attendee of physics conferences; and as a writer of published academic papers, nonfiction works for a general audience, and of mathematical and logic puzzles with science and sports as their subject matter. Some personal materials, largely documenting Spruch's travels and interests in progressive politics and theatre, are also included in the collection. Formats of materials in the collection include lecture notes, examination forms, unpublished dissertations and theses, correspondence and memoranda, conference programs, reprints and preprints of academic papers, research proposals, handwritten notes and manuscripts, and news clippings. A small number of photographs are also present in Series VII.
The materials in the collection are arranged into series and subseries according to the functions by which they were created and used. The contents of each series and subseries are described in more detail in the series-level scope and content notes.
Access Restrictions
Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Arrangement
The current order of the Larry Spruch Papers is not original. However, certain aspects of the arrangement imposed by the archivist are meant to reflect the order in which Larry Spruch seems to have originally kept them, insofar as that order can be perceived.
The folders within most series are arranged in chronological order, with two exceptions. Series II: Correspondence is arranged in alphabetical order by the correspondent's last name. Likewise, Series IV, Subseries B: Works by Other Physicists, is arranged in alphabetical order by author's last name or—where authors' names are not given—by publication or subject matter. (See the Scope and Content note for more information about the contents of Series IV, Subseries B: Works by Other Physicists).
The collection is arranged into eight series, three of which have been further divided into subseries:
The current order of the Larry Spruch Papers is not original. The materials are arranged into series and subseries in the collection according to the functions by which they were created and used.
The folders within most series are arranged in chronological order, with one exception. Series IV, Subseries B: Works by Other Physicists, is arranged in alphabetical order by author's last name or—where multiple authors' works were included in the same folder—by publication or subject matter.
The collection is arranged into eight series, three of which have been further divided into subseries:
Missing Title
New York University
Correspondence
China-U.S. Physics Examination and Application (CUSPEA) Program
Professional Materials
Research
University of Pennsylvania Coursework
Personal Materials
Sports Quizzes
2019 Accretion
Related Materials
The following website was created by the New York University Department of Physics to honor Larry Spruch in 2001. It contains biographical information, a bibliography, and several papers written by Spruch's closest colleagues in appreciation of his contributions to physics.
Larry Spruch, 1923-2006
Biography of Larry Spruch
Theoretical physicist Larry Spruch (1923-2006) was a longtime member of the faculty of the Department of Physics at New York University. He was born on January 1, 1923, in Brooklyn, New York, and earned a B.S. from Brooklyn College in 1943. He then enrolled in the University of Pennsylvania as a Ph.D. candidate in Physics. His thesis work, "On the beta decay of the triton" (1948), was supervised by Leonard I. Schiff.
While attending the University of Pennsylvania, Spruch was an instructor from 1943 to 1946 and a Tyndale Fellow from 1946 to 1948. After earning his Ph.D., he became an Atomic Energy Commission Postdoctoral Fellow at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, working on problems in nuclear physics with Herman Feshbach and Victor Weisskopf. After two years at MIT, Spruch accepted the position of Assistant Professor at New York University in 1950. He was promoted to Associate Professor in 1955 and full Professor in 1961. Upon his official retirement in 1994, he was honored with Professor Emeritus status.
Spruch taught a variety of courses for graduate and undergraduate students at NYU. Some would be expected of a professor with a background in theoretical nuclear and atomic physics: Scattering Theory, Quantum Mechanics, Electricity and Magnetism, and Mathematical Physics, among others. Yet he also taught a series of courses intended to make physics accessible to non-majors, by illustrating its relevance to everyday life in layman's terms. These courses included Physics and Society, Physics for Poets, and Intelligent Life in the Universe. As of 1998, Spruch had also supervised 21 Ph.D. dissertations and 17 postdoctoral fellowships at NYU.
In addition to teaching, Spruch was a very active researcher. His work covered a wide range of issues in nuclear and particle physics, as well as selected topics in astrophysics. Throughout the course of his career, he published over 150 scientific papers in journals such as The Physical Review, Journal of Mathematical Physics, and Nuclear Physics. He also served as guest editor, with James F. Babb and Peter W. Milonni, of a special issue of Comments on Modern Physics on Casimir forces in 2000. Spruch is best known for his developments in scattering theory, investigations of Casimir forces, and contributions to the problem of determining necessary conditions for the existence of bound states. He frequently collaborated with other physicists in conducting research, most notably Edward Gerjuoy, Yukap Hahn, Edward Kelsey, Thomas F. O'Malley, A. R. P. Rau, Leonard Rosenberg, and Robin Shakeshaft.
Spruch further contributed to his field through service as a member of the editorial boards of The Physical Review A and Zeitschrift für Physik A, a correspondent for Comments on Atomic and Molecular Physics, and a consultant for Lawrence Livermore Laboratory and Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory. He also served as part of a delegation of scholars for the China-U.S. Physics Examination and Application (CUSPEA) program. CUSPEA was an examination and admission system used by the physics departments of selected American and Canadian universities for graduate student applicants from the People's Republic of China between 1979 and 1989. Along with other physics professors from participating North American universities, Spruch assisted with interviewing applicants and the preparation of exam questions. He traveled to China in 1985 as part of his work with CUSPEA.
Spruch's career was marked by numerous awards and honors. Highlights include the Atomic Energy Commission Fellowship (1948-50), National Science Foundation Senior Postdoctoral Fellowship for the University of London and Oxford University (1963-64), Brooklyn College's Alumni Award for Merit (1967), membership in the Institute for Advanced Study at Princeton University (1981), the Alexander von Humboldt Award (1985), the NYU Golden Dozen Teaching Award (1991), and the Davisson-Germer Prize (1992). For the Alexander von Humboldt Award, Spruch cooperated on a long-term research project with colleagues at the Max Planck Institut Für Kernphysik in Heidelberg, Germany. In addition to these awards, Spruch attended and spoke at more than 100 conferences around the world, and attended the summer Aspen Center for Physics in Aspen, Colorado, for 30 years.
Larry Spruch shared with his wife, the physicist Grace Marmor Spruch, an interest in making science and mathematics accessible and interesting to the general public. The pair co-authored a series of quizzes which appeared monthly in the magazine The Sciences, and were later collected and published as 21 Astounding Science Quizzes! The Spruchs also published The Ubiquitous Atom!, a book which describes the foundations of atomic physics and its applications to biology, genetics, medicine, and archaeology. Larry Spruch spent several years developing and refining a collection of mathematics and logic puzzles with a sports theme, but that manuscript remains unpublished.
After his official retirement, Larry Spruch continued his physics research at New York University. He died on August 10, 2006, in New York City.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Larry Spruch Papers were transferred from Larry Spruch's office to the University Archives by his widow, Grace Marmor Spruch, in 2006. In April 2019, an accretion was donated by Susan Smolin, executor of the Grace Marmor Spruch estate; the accession number associated with this gift is 2019.050.
Nuclear physics.; Physics -- Study and teaching -- United States; Mathematical physics; Thomas-Fermi theory; Astrophysics; Casimir effect; Scattering (Mathematics); Bound states (Quantum mechanics); Puzzles; Scattering length (Nuclear physics); Shakeshaft, Robin; Hahn, Yukap; Schaden, Martin; Zhou, Fei; Wadehra, Jogindra M.; Borowitz, Sidney, 1918-; Rau, A. R. P. (A. Ravi P.); Spruch, Grace Marmor; New York University -- Faculty -- 20th century
- Series I: New York University, 1950-1999
  Scope and Content
  Series I contains materials dating from between 1950 and 1999, created through Larry Spruch's activities as a professor of Physics at New York University. The series is divided into three subseries.
  Subseries A: Course Materials contains lecture notes, problem books, quizzes, and exams from the undergraduate and graduate level Physics courses which Spruch taught. It also contains news clippings and other materials used in Spruch's popular Physics and Society course, which discussed the relationship between physics and current events and was geared toward non-Physics majors. Some preliminary examinations for the Ph.D. in Physics dating from between 1967 and 1990 are included in the series. Finally, a few folders of materials from NYU courses which Spruch may have audited, such as Literature of Modern Ireland, are present in Subseries A.
  Subseries B: Faculty and Administrative Affairs contains materials related to Spruch's non-teaching duties at NYU. As such, it includes memoranda and other materials reflecting the activities of the Physics department and the larger NYU faculty. It also contains documentation of Spruch's activities while on sabbatical from NYU.
  Subseries C: Student Theses and Dissertations includes drafts and final copies of theses and dissertations which were created under Spruch's supervision, or in which Spruch took an interest.
  - Subseries A: Course Materials, 1950-1999
    - Field Theory lecture notes, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Final exams from various courses taught by Spruch, 1950-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Physics 33/161/171: Thermodynamics, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Physics 22/193/194: Atomic Physics, 1951-1952, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Physics 171 final exam, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Physics 194, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Special Topics lecture notes, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Physics 193: Atomic Physics, 1952-1953, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Exams for Physics 193 and 194: Atomic Physics and Physics 272: Electricity and Magnetism, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Physics 271 final exam, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Physics 291, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Richard Feynman's lecture notes on quantum dynamics, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Physics 194, 271, 610, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Quantum Theory lecture notes, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Physics 271: Electricity and Magnetism, 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Physics 101, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Physics 101 final exam, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Quantum Mechanics, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Physics 271 final exam, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Electricity and Magnetism lecture notes and exam forms, 1953-1959 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Scattering Theory lecture notes, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Physics 211: Dynamics, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Physics 211: Dynamics final exam, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Physics 212 problems, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Physics 212 final exam, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Physics 292: Quantum Theory exam, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Physics 293: Quantum Mechanics exam, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Physics 101 midterm exam, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Physics 291: Quantum Mechanics final exam, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Physics 271: Electricity and Magnetism problems, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Scattering Theory lecture notes and problems, 1955-1960 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Physics 101, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Math 254, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Physics 272: Electricity and Magnetism, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Electricity and Magnetism final exam, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Field Theory lecture notes, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Physics 295: Nuclear Theory, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Nuclear Physics problems, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Physics 263: Scattering Theory, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Physics 263: Scattering Theory, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Physics 265: Nuclear Theory, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Physics 263: Scattering Theory, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Physics 277: Quantum Mechanics, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Resource Letters published by the American Journal of Physics for college professors, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Quantum Mechanics, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Quantum Mechanics midterm, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Introduction to Theoretical Physics, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Nuclear Theory lecture notes, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Physics of Elementary Particles, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Lecture notes on variational principles, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Physics 2201: Mathematical Methods, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Scattering Theory course materials, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Quantum Theory course, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Problems from Goldberger and Watson, Collision Theory, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Particles, Waves, and Wave Mechanics notes for students by Sidney Borowitz, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Modern Theater, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Physics 1132: Quantum Mechanics, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Mathematical Methods for Theoretical Physics, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Quantum Mechanics final exam, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Physics for Poets, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Lecture notes and problems on cosmology, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Astrophysics "Odds and Ends", 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Undergraduate Quantum Mechanics course, 1967-1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Quantum Mechanics final exams, 1967, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Physics for Poets, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Physics for Poets, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Undergraduate Astrophysics, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Physics for Poets, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Astrophysics materials for Physics for Poets, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Physics and Society, 1969-1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Physics and Society, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Physics and Society course description, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Physics and Society, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Math. Methods II syllabus, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Physics and Society exams, 1973-1974, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Problems for Mathematical Physics: Green's functions, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - NYU undergraduate colloquium, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Electricity and Magnetism, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Quantum Mechanics, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Barger and Olsson, Classical Mechanics: problems and notes, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Class handout on the hydrogen bomb, circa 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Physics 16: Intelligent Life in the Universe, 1978-1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Notes on nuclear physics for Physics and Society class, 1978-1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Space Age Astronomy final exam, 1978, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Barger and Olsson's Mechanics: problems and notes; Dynamics final exam, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Physics and Society, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Physics and Society, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Physics and Society lecture notes, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Clippings for Physics and Society, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Notes and clippings for Physics and Society, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - New Yorker articles for Physics and Society, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Quantum Mechanics exam solutions, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Physics and Society, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Physics and Society exams, 1979-1981, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Quantum Mechanics II, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Physics and Society reports, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Quantum Mechanics, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Physics and Society, 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Undergraduate Mathematical Physics final exam, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Physics 606: problem sets from Jackson text, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Undergraduate Mathematical Physics notes, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Graduate-level Quantum Mechanics exam, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Undergraduate Mathematical Physics final exam, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Notes and clippings for Physics and Society, 1981-1986 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Intelligent Life in the Universe, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Intelligent Life in the Universe, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Undergraduate Mathematical Physics final exam, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Intelligent Life in the Universe, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Space Age Astronomy, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Undergraduate Mathematical Physics final exam, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Rough notes on diagonalization of matrices, for undergraduate Mathematical Physics course, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Electromagnetism II, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Space Age Astronomy Make-up Exam, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Astrophysics problems, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Undergraduate Mathematical Physics notes, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Mathematical Physics final exam, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Atomic Physics problems, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Atomic Physics, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Electricity and Magnetism problems from Jackson, Classical Electrodynamics (2nd ed.), 1984, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Electromagnetism exam, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Problems from Jackson, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Physics and Society, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Notes and problems from Jackson, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Electromagnetism I and II, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Electromagnetism I and II final exams, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Electromagnetism I, 1985-1988 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Notes and clippings for Physics and Society, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Electricity and Magnetism and Quantum Mechanics problems and exams, 1986, 1990-1998 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Notes on quantum mechanics for Physics and Society, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Notes and clippings for Physics and Society, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Physics and Society exams, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Notes on Jackson text for Electricity and Magnetism, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Problems for Electricity and Magnetism, Quantum Mechanics, and Mathematical Physics, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Electricity and Magnetism problem book, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Quantum Optics, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - French Revolution course materials, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Electricity and Magnetism problems, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Quantum Mechanics I problems, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Quantum Mechanics problems, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Quantum Field Theory lecture notes, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Virial theorem proof, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Quantum Mechanics problems from Cohen-Tannoudji, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Quantum Mechanics final exam, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Quantum Mechanics II, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Quantum Mechanics II final exam, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Electromagnetism I, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Electricity and Magnetism, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Quantum Mechanics II problems, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Quantum Mechanics problem book, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Electricity and Magnetism I final exam, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Electromagnetism I final exam, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Electromagnetism I final exam, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Notes on quantum computation, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Electromagnetism I midterm, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Electromagnetism II, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Electromagnetism II problems, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Electromagnetism I problems, checked by Shidong Zhang, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Phase Transitions and Critical Phenomena (taught by Alan Sokal), 1994 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Scattering Theory problems, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Problems for Quantum Mechanics and Electricity and Magnetism, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Electricity and Magnetism problem book, checked by Shidong Ziang, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Electricity and Magnetism I problems, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Electromagnetism I final exam, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Electromagnetism II, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Problems checked by Shidong Zhang, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Thermodynamics problem book, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Quantum Mechanics problems, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Quantum Mechanics problems from Sakurai, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Quantum Mechanics problem book, checked by Shidong Jiang, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Quantum Mechanics I midterm, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Quantum Mechanics I final exam, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Electricity and Magnetism problem book, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Electromagnetism and Quantum Mechanics problem book, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Electromagnetism II problems, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Electromagnetism II exam, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Mathematical Physics problem book, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Mathematical Physics problems, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Pion-nucleon scattering problem book, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Quantum Mechanics problems, 1996-1998 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Quantum mechanics problems from Sakurai, 1996-1998 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Quantum Mechanics I midterm, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Quantum Mechanics problems, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 39)